A Guide to the Commonwealth Fund records, Pilgrim Trust, SG 1, Series 28 FA300
Rockefeller Archive Center
Commonwealth Fund records, Pilgrim Trust, SG 1, Series 28
1930-1977
1930-1950
Rockefeller Archive Center
Commonwealth Fund
FA300
2.47 Cubic Feet 6 document boxes and 1 half-box.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Biographical/Historical note
The Commonwealth Fund was established in 1918 with an endowment of $10 million from Mrs. Stephen V. Harkness for "benevolent, religious, educational and like purposes." The early grants supported a variety of programs while generally promoting welfare, especially child welfare. Several grants were made in the field of medical research, but the Board of Directors decided in 1920 that this field was already sufficiently supported by other philanthropic organizations.
Despite this decision, by the mid-1920s the chief interest of the Fund had become public health, including mental hygiene, community health, rural hospitals, medical research, and medical education. Other grant areas included war relief, educational and legal research, child welfare, and international medical fellowships.
File Plan note
Former Classification: IX; IV 4B 4
Biographical / Historical
The Pilgrim Trust was established by Edward S. Harkness in 1930, with an endowment of 2 million pound sterling. The stated mission of the Trust was to assist Great Britian and Northern Ireland with "urgent needs".
Scope and Contents
Pilgrim Trust records primarily consist of Annual Reports, Minutes, and a variety of newspaper clippings.
Other Finding Aids
Other available finding aids describing the Commonwealth Fund records include:
FA247 Commonwealth Fund Harkness House drawings
FA276 Commonwealth Fund records, Annual Reports, SG 1, Series 4
FA277 Commonwealth Fund records, Archives/Library, SG 1, Series 5
FA278 Commonwealth Fund records, Austrian Program, SG 1, Series 6
FA279 Commonwealth Fund records, Board of Directors, SG 1, Series 7
FA280 Commonwealth Fund records, Capital Grants, SG 1, Series 8
FA281 Commonwealth Fund records, Child Health Demonstrations, SG 1, Series 9
FA282 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Community Clinics, SG 1, Series 10
FA283 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Health Studies, SG 1, Series 11
FA284 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Public Health, SG 1, Series 12
FA285 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Publications, SG 1, Series 13
FA286 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Rural Hospitals, SG 1, Series 14
FA287 Commonwealth Fund records, Educational Research, SG 1, Series 15
FA288 Commonwealth Fund records, English Mental Hygiene Program, SG 1, Series 16
FA289 Commonwealth Fund records, Finance Committee, SG 1, Series 17
FA290 Commonwealth Fund records, Grants, SG 1, Series 18
FA291 Commonwealth Fund records, Harkness Family, SG 1, Series 19
FA292 Commonwealth Fund records, Harkness Fellowships, SG 1, Series 20
FA428 Commonwealth Fund records, Harkness Fellowships, Fellows Reports, SG 1, Series 20A
FA293 Commonwealth Fund records, Institute for Child Guidance, SG 1, Series 21
FA294 Commonwealth Fund records, Interface Program, SG 1, Series 22
FA295 Commonwealth Fund records, Legal Research Program, SG 1, Series 23
FA296 Commonwealth Fund records, Living at Home Program, SG 1, Series 24
FA297 Commonwealth Fund records, Mental Hygiene Program, SG 1, Series 25
FA298 Commonwealth Fund records, Miscellaneous - unprocessed
FA299 Commonwealth Fund records, Personnel - unprocessed
FA300 Commonwealth Fund records, Pilgrim Trust, SG 1, Series 28
FA301 Commonwealth Fund records, Program for the Prevention of Delinquency, SG 1, Series 29
FA302 Commonwealth Fund records, Reference Files, SG 1, Series 30
FA303 Commonwealth Fund records, Reports of the General Director, SG 1, Series 31
FA304 Commonwealth Fund records, Treasurer, SG 1, Series 32
FA305 Commonwealth Fund records, Turndown Lists, SG 1, Series 33 - unprocessed
FA306 Commonwealth Fund records, Vertical File (R. Fitz), SG 1, Series 34 - unprocessed
FA307 Commonwealth Fund records, Visual Materials, SG 1, Series 35
FA389 Commonwealth Fund records, Administration - Historical Files, SG 1, Series 1
FA390 Commonwealth Fund records, Administration - Officers Files, SG 1, Series 2
FA429 Commonwealth Fund records, President, Margaret E. Mahoney, SG 2, Series 1
FA430 Commonwealth Fund records, Book Program, SG 2, Series 2
Child psychology; Child mental health; New York (N.Y.); New York (State); Public health; Public welfare; United States; War relief; Medical research; Medical education; Legal research; Legal issues; Law; Hygiene; Education, Rural; Child welfare; Mental health; Medicine, Rural; Medicine -- Scholarships, fellowships, etc.
- Annual Report, 1930-1931 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Annual Report, 1932-1933 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Annual Report, 1933-1934 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Annual Report, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Annual Report, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Annual Report, 1936-1937 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Annual Report, 1937-1938 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Annual Report, 1938-1939 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Annual Report, 1939-1940 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Annual Report, 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Annual Report, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Annual Report, 1943-1945 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Annual Report, 1945-1946 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Annual Report, 1947-1948 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Annual Report, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Annual Reports, 1950-1952 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Annual Reports, 1953-1955 (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Annual Reports, 1956-1958 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Annual Reports, 1959-1960, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Annual Reports, 1965, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Annual Report, 1976-1977 (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Minutes, 1930-1931 (Box 5, Folder 22)
- Minutes, 1932 (Box 5, Folder 23)
- Minutes, 1933 (Box 5, Folder 24)
- Minutes, 1934 (Box 5, Folder 25)
- Minutes, 1935 (Box 6, Folder 26)
- Minutes, 1936 (Box 6, Folder 27)
- Minutes, 1937 (Box 6, Folder 28)
- Minutes, 1938 (Box 7, Folder 29)
- Supplementary Material, 1928-1929, 1931 (Box 7, Folder 30)
- Clippings (Box 7, Folder 31)